Finding Aid for Cavanagh Family papers, 1857-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cavanagh Family papers 1857-2006
Cavanagh Family
1.5 linear ft. and 1 oversize folder
0665 Aa 2; UAm
Members of the Cavanagh family have resided in Yale, St. Clair County, Michigan since 1857. The collection was accumulated by Martha Cavanagh Cameron and consists of original and copied materials of various Cavanagh and Johnston family members.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Martha Cavanagh Cameron (donor no. 9665 ) and came to the library in April 2006.
The collection is open to research.
The Cavanagh family were early settlers to St. Clair County, Michigan, specifically to Brockway Township and the city of Yale. Andrew Cavanagh immigrated from Ireland to Ontario, Canada. In 1857, he came to Port Huron to work in the lumber business. While there, he looked for farm land to buy and where he could raise his family. In 1861, he purchased some property and moved to Brockway Township. He and his wife Annie McKay raised eight children.
Two of their sons, George and Justin were owners of the Princess movie theater in Yale, Michigan, purchased on September 18, 1915. In 1919, George bought out Justin's shares in the theater and continued for many years thereafter as sole proprietor.
On March 27, 1901, George Cavanagh had married Margaret Johnston. They had two sons, Herbert A. and Max H.
Another family member, George's nephew, Charles Andrew Cavanagh, was under-sheriff of St. Clair County. In 1934, he was killed in the line of duty by a companion of John Dillinger, recently escaped from jail.
The Cavanagh family papers have been arranged into an alphabetical series. The files have been arranged by name of family member with a few exceptions for general family and Yale related files. Of special note are the diaries of George Cavanagh, who was proprietor of the Princess movie theater in Yale, Michigan beginning in 1915.
Subjects:
Cavanaugh family.; Cavanagh, George, 1872-1950.; Johnston family.; Motion picture theaters--Michigan--Yale.; Saint Clair County (Mich.); Yale (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cavanaugh family.; Johnston family.; Yale (Mich.)
Contributors:
Cameron, Martha Cavanagh.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Family Papers
  - Cavanagh history, photographs, birth and death information (Box 1)
    (see also oversize photographs)
  - Andrew Cavanagh diary, 1857 (Box 1)
    (brief descriptions of weather and activities)
  - Andrew Cavanagh writings, 1873-1897 (Box 1)
    (include notebook with accounts and jottings, letter, etc.)
  - George and Margaret (Johnston) Cavanagh papers, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (include photographs, clippings, and other papers)
    (see also oversize photograph of George Cavanagh as member of a group of rural mail carrier)
  - George Cavanagh diaries, 1905-1922, 19 volumes (Box 1)
    (descriptions of weather, operation of the movie theatre with comments on the movies and the stars, community events, and family matters)
  - Justin Cavanagh letters, clippings, poetry, and photographs (Box 1)
  - Princess Theater (Yale, Michigan) (Box 1)
    (initially owned jointly by brothers George and Justin Cavanagh)
  - Belle L. Cavanagh autograph book, 1880s (Box 2)
    (daughter of Andrew Cavanagh)
  - Herbert A. Cavanagh papers, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
    (son of George and Margaret Cavanagh)
  - Herbert and Mildred Patterson Cavanagh papers, 1904-1980 (Box 2)
    (include photographs and memorabilia)
  - Max and Rita Cavanagh papers, 1914-1983 (Box 2)
    (Max was son of George and Margaret Cavanagh; include photographs and memorabilia)
  - Charles Andrew Cavanagh and family, ca. 1935-1980s (Box 2)
    (nephew of George Cavanagh; includes clippings, photographs, and cd of newspaper articles about his shooting and of photographs)
  - Johnston family papers (Box 2)
    (include photographs and memorabilia; see also oversize photograph Johnston brothers, 1912)
  - Yale, Michigan, history and personages (Box 2)
    (clippings and published material)
  - Yale School (K-12) (Box 2)
    (newspaper articles and rolled photograph of students)
  - Videotape (vhs) of motion pictures made by Herbert A. Cavanagh of family members, their activities, views of Yale and surrounding area, ca. 1930s-1940s (Box 2)